<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Barvvick bridge: or England and Scotland coupled In a sermon tending to peace and vnitie. Preached before the King at Saint Andrewes in Scotland. Anno Domini. 1617. Iulij 13. By Robert Wilkinson Dr. in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102764</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2911</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2911)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1123:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Barvvick bridge: or England and Scotland coupled In a sermon tending to peace and vnitie. Preached before the King at Saint Andrewes in Scotland. Anno Domini. 1617. Iulij 13. By Robert Wilkinson Dr. in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for William Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running titles read: The praises of peace.</note>
                  <note>Also issued with title page cancelled as part 1 of STC 25664: Robert Wilkinson. Three sermons (1617).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2911:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2911:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Barwick bridge: OR ENGLAND <hi rend="smallCaps">AND</hi> SCOTLAND COVPLED.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon tending to peace and vnitie.</p>
            <p>Preached before the King at Saint <hi rend="smallCaps">ANDREWES</hi> in <hi rend="smallCaps">SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anno Domini. 1617. Iulij. 13.</p>
            <p>By <hi rend="smallCaps">ROBERT WILKINSON</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. in Diuinitie, and Chaplaine to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="smallCaps">ESAY</hi> 19. 23.</bibl> In that day there ſhall be a path from Aegypt to Aſhur, and Aſhur ſhall come into Aegypt, and Aegypt into Aſhur, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallCaps">LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi rend="smallCaps">EDWARD GRIFFIN</hi> for <hi>William Aspley.</hi> 1617.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2911:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2911:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY</hi> JAMES, <hi>BY the grace of God, King of great <hi rend="smallCaps">BRITAINE, FRANCE</hi> and <hi rend="smallCaps">IRELAND,</hi> &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Enowned and Beloued of God and man: As the Wiſemen followed the ſtarre in the Eaſt, ſo haue wee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed your Maieſty into the North, at your appointment wee haue preacht, and now at your command I haue put my ſelfe into the preſſe; To which I might haue anſwered, as one of the ſons in the Gospell, yea, as one of your Presbyterian ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits lately anſwered you; <hi>Nolo,</hi> in flat terms I will not obey you; for why ſhould ſo many men, the choiſe of two famous Churches, of ſo much greater learning of more and more excellent gifts, whom you haue heard not with attention only, but with admiration too, why (I ſay) ſhould ſuch and ſo manie eſcape the
<pb facs="tcp:2911:3"/> publiſhing, &amp; I only to be ſet vpon the ſtage? yet I aske it not of your Maieſtie, but of my ſelfe; and I thinke I haue found the reaſon of it, for as <hi>Izaak</hi> could not but know, that <hi>Iacob</hi> was better then <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> and yet loued <hi>Eſau</hi> for the meat which hee brought him, ſo your Maieſty knoweth that there be in our ſociety, who like <hi>Rebecca</hi> can make bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter veniſon of a kid, then I haue done of veniſon, &amp; yet you haue thus deſigned on me; therfore it was not I, but the argument, euen the peace (I ſpake of) which ſo affected you; eſpecially to heare of peace in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but more eſpecially to heare of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> the very meat vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly which your ſoule loueth: and therefore while I ſeeme to publiſh my Sermon, I print vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares your Maieſties praiſe, and make knowen to the world how highly your Highnes apprizeth peace; yea we haue lately ſeene it with our eies, that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> &amp; <hi>Peace</hi> are met in you, we haue ſeen you ſitting in Parliament ten daies together, &amp; we are witneſſes that once you ſat from one at noone to ten at night; ſo much is Iuſtice beholden to you; And we haue hard from your Maieſtie nothing here ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding but loue &amp; peace, you haue in your open Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament profeſſed your loue to our Engliſh Nation;
<pb facs="tcp:2911:3"/> you haue proclaimed great puniſhment on ſuch as ſhould abuſe the meaneſt of our nation; you haue been of nothing more carefull then of our entertainment, &amp; ſuch as haue kindly entertained vs, you haue open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thanked, you haue knighted &amp; honoured them for it; that as the <hi>Babylonians</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cyrus, The King is become a Iew,</hi> ſo your Maieſtie at this time hath been whollie Engliſh but it is your loue, as in <hi>England</hi> to cheriſh Scots, ſo in <hi>Scotland</hi> to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs, and euerie where to be kinde to ſtrangers, &amp; it is your wiſdom ſo to loue vs both, that your example might worke loue &amp; peace in both. And ſince we are returned in peace, firſt, with <hi>Iacob</hi> we ſet vp a piller of thanks to him who hath kept vs in our iourney; &amp; next to your Maieſtie we giue, at leaſt we repay the thankes which you your ſelfe vouchſafed your owne Subiects in our behalfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; for thoſe your Subiects, we reioice to thinke that in all this time of our intercourſe &amp; abode amongst them, we haue had no combate, but of kindes with them, &amp; in kindnes (we confeſſe) they haue euercome vs: yea, from the great <hi>Lo: Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of Scotland</hi> to the Colledge hals &amp; Burgers houſes, we are debters &amp; priſoners, &amp; for entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that quality, as if anie man ſhall depraue it, he is like thoſe men which raile on the Sun, &amp; like the
<pb facs="tcp:2911:4"/> dogs which bark at the moone; yea, if any man ſhall embaſe what wee haue found ſo honourable, if hee were partaker of the iourney, I ſay, he is wilfully mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, but if he ſpeak by heare-ſay, his heare-ſay is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, &amp; he is falſly &amp; vncharitably credulous, yea if <hi>Scotland</hi> were as barren, as ſome report, which haue not ſeen it, we might report it for a wonder, that <hi>God hath prepared vs a table in the wildernes,</hi> for euery where we haue found cheerfull welcome, willing attendance, and of all things ſuch abundance, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bee complained of, but exceſſe, or if any thing were worſe then that exceſſe, wee our ſelues brought it with vs, it was our owne vnthankfulnes: yea if our beaſts could ſpeake, they would acknowledge fulnes of the crib, &amp; ſay out of the Prophet <hi>Eſay, we haue eaten cleane prouander winnowed and fanned,</hi> and ſhew themſelues more thankfull to their benefactors, then many of their owners haue beene to God. That God, who hath euery where abundantly fed vs, who hath kept vs abroad, &amp; brought vs ſafely home, that God make vs thankfull to himſelfe, &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to them who haue well deſerued of vs, and vpon your Maieſty (we beſeech him) ſo to deriue the peace-makers bleſsing heere, as you may bee called eternally the ſonne of God heereafter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties euer moſt obliged and dutifull Chaplaine</hi> Robert Wilkinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2911:4"/>
            <head>THE PRAISES OF PEACE. A Sermon preached at Saint <hi rend="smallCaps">ANDREWES</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 133. 1.</bibl> Behold how good and pleaſant it is for brethren to dwell together in one.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Excellent:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, Right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, Beloued and Chriſtian Brethren; we are heere aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled a mixt and great aſſembly of two great Kingdomes; for which cauſe I haue taken a text of congratulation: and we are met among other reaſons (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture) to giue thankes that wee may thus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2911:5"/> meet, to reioyce in God, and to be mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally merry, and for that cauſe I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen a text out of a Pſalme; yea, I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen a text out of a Pſalme, which (as <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith) is <hi>notus &amp; nominatus,</hi> a Pſalme well knowen to euery man, and much ſpoken of in euery mouth; and he ſaith of the text, that it is <hi>ſonus ita dulcis,</hi> ſo ſweet a ſound, as many which knew not the <hi>Pſalter,</hi> yet could ſing the verſe, &amp; diuers which could not reade, yet had it by rote, <hi>Ecce quam bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant it is for brethren to dwell together.</hi> The Pſalme was penned by <hi>Dauid,</hi> and at that time (as it is thought, when after long warre betwixt the two houſes of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſome of the Tribes taking one part, and ſome another, they all came in at laſt, and ſwore fealty to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and made him King; the ſweet ſenſe whereof makes him to write this Pſalme, and to breake out into this exclamation, <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant it is, &amp;c.</hi> And it is as if he had ſayd, Compare the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the time paſt, and ſee what a change is made, while you had two Kings,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2911:5"/> you had them as two ſwords reuelling in the bowels of the Kingdomes, but now God hath ſet an vnion in your diuiſions, &amp; quietneſſe in your borders, yea, hee hath ſtampt vnity vpon your coyne, <hi>Faciam eos in gentem vnam,</hi> all to haue one King, &amp; all to make as it were one Kingdome; while you were diuided into parts, one part was ſtill a prey to another, and as <hi>Abner</hi> ſpake to <hi>Ioab,</hi> the ſword of ech deuoured other: but now God hath broken your ſwords into mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks, and your ſpeares into ſithes: Figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is now turned to feaſting, and force of armes to mutuall embracing, ſo as now you may ſafely viſit the Coaſts, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and Townes, and Cities, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Vniuerſities, and Colledges each of other, <hi>Ecce quam bonum, Behold how good and pleaſant this is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The maine ſubiect of the text is Peace; not the peace betwixt a man and his owne conſcience, which <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. is called <hi>Reſt to your ſoules:</hi> nor yet the peace betwixt God &amp; man, wher of <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. Being iuſtified by faith we haue peace toward God: but it is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2911:6"/> the peace betwixt brethren, that is, betwixt man and man; concerning which we may in the text obſerue theſe fiue things. Firſt, it is deſcribed by a phraſe of <hi>dwelling together:</hi> Secondly, it is limited, only among <hi>brethren.</hi> Thirdly, it is commended to be <hi>good</hi> and to be <hi>pleaſant.</hi> Fourthly, it is admired, <hi>How</hi> good and <hi>How</hi> pleaſant. Fiftly, it is poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at, <hi>Behold</hi> how good, and <hi>Behold</hi> how pleaſant: of all which by your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Gods aſsiſtance, I will ſpeake in order.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the firſt; The peace heere mentioned is ſtiled a dwelling, and a dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling together; and firſt a <hi>dwelling,</hi> for peace is as a man ſettled and quiet in his owne houſe, which followes not vaine pomp &amp; pride, nor yet the tumults and reſtleſſe troubles, nor toſsing and tumbling vp and downe the world, but peace ſaith as God ſaith in the Pſalme next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Hic requies mea, heere will I dwell.</hi> But they to whom there is no peace, they are like the raging ſea which cannot reſt, <hi>Eſay</hi> 57. and <hi>Prou.</hi> 4. they cannot ſleepe vnleſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2911:6"/> they haue done euill; and no maruell; for Sathan their head is a ranger, he dwels no where, but euery where, <hi>Hee compaſſeth the earth, and walketh in it Iob</hi> 1, and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>He walketh vp and downe like a roaring Lyon, ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king whom he may deuoure:</hi> The tyrants of the earth which are his left hand, they dwell or reſt no where, but run out to the North and South, and Eaſt and Weſt, and extend their Dominions <hi>ouer the whole earth. Dan.</hi> 8. Againe, Phariſies &amp; falſe Prophets, which are his right hand, <hi>they compaſſe ſea &amp; land to make a man of their profeſsion.</hi> yet their diligence makes no warrant for their ill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours; It is ſayd of the harlot <hi>Prou.</hi> 7. <hi>that her feet cannot abide in her houſe, but now ſhe is without, and now in the ſtreets, and lieth in waite at euery corner.</hi> The myſticall propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of ſchiſme and ſeducing hereſie: for ſo doe the Prieſts, but eſpecially the reſtles Ieſuites, they are no where ſettled, but wander vp and downe like Apoſtles, and though S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd, <hi>that God had ſet foorth them the laſt Apoſtles.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. yet they are Apoſtles later then the laſt, and becauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2911:7"/> God will not ſend them out, they therfore ſend out themſelues, and runne to the <hi>Indies</hi> Eaſt and Weſt, to <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> to the <hi>Moluccoes,</hi> and to the great <hi>Magueere,</hi> and if we may beleeue their owne reports, they haue been in the remote and mighty king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>China,</hi> they haue beene at all Coaſts and Capes, and ſeas and wayes, only the way of peace they haue not knowen. Againe, peace is not a dwelling onely, but a dwelling <hi>together?</hi> together? how! not <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul in crimine,</hi> like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui,</hi> brethren in iniquity, combined in ſinne together: nor <hi>ſimul in certamine,</hi> as <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> or as of late two popiſh prelates in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for meere precedency, &amp; in a Church, flatly by the eares together; but <hi>together</hi> is heere cohabiting together, in a city, in a houſe, in a Church together, and ſometime as <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 13. <hi>in a chamber together:</hi> and which is the moralitie of all this, <hi>of one heart and ſoule together. Acts</hi> 4. 32. And indeede wee ſee in nature, that the peaceable and harmleſſe creatures do flocke together like doues, and folde together like ſheepe: but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2911:7"/> wolues, and lyons, and beares, which lie in wait for blood, they liue in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and apart, and owles come out in the night and apart, and make a noyſe when all the reſt of the birds are aſleepe, but they are neither good <hi>intympano,</hi> nor <hi>in choro,</hi> they ſing not in conſort, and when they ſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, it is the very horror of muſique; and ſo it is obſerued among men; if a man bee too much retired, and ſolitary, and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, &amp; hang downe his head like <hi>Cain,</hi> &amp; like <hi>Shemaiah</hi> become a Recluſe and ſhut vp himſelfe, euerie man ſtraight will vſe the prouerb vpon ſuch an one, <hi>Omnis ſolitarius aut Deus aut Daemon,</hi> ſuch a man may bee a Saint, and hee may as well bee a Diuell; It was the aduantage which Chriſt had of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, that he liued in cities &amp; townes, and did eat and drinke, and was ſociable, ſo as he baptized, and all men came to him: <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. but <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> liued in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe auſterely and ſourely, and came nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eating nor drinking, ſo as they which knew not the myſterie of it, ſaid plainely, that <hi>Iohn had a Diuell, Matth.</hi> 11. And we ſee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2911:8"/> for the moſt part that theſe cloſe and ſullen ſpirits, looke whatſoeuer way they take, they become by their ſingularitie hurtfull; if they haue to do in the ſtate, they become proud and contentions, and breed factions there: if they haue to doe in learning, they proue dogmaticall, full of paradoxes and of opinions there; but if in the Church, they are not onely ſchiſmaticall, but turbulent and pragmaticall, and with <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> ready to make riot, if all be not to their will; oh how peaceable had it been for the Church, how ſtrong for the field, and how happy for the whole world, if ſuch <hi>Church-men</hi> had beene made ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; but euery man if he be a Saint is of the Communion of Saints, and they which be truely brethren, doe dwell, and liue, and die together; The word in the text impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth more, euen to dwell together in <hi>vnity,</hi> or in <hi>one.</hi> Now as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, there bee many wayes of <hi>one,</hi> there is <hi>vnitas collectiua,</hi> as when many ſtones make one heape, &amp; there is <hi>vnitas conſtitutiua,</hi> as when many members make one body, and there is <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2911:8"/> 
               <hi>coniugatiua,</hi> as when man and woman make one fleſh, and there is <hi>vnitas natiua,</hi> as when fleſh and ſpirit make vp one man, with diuers other kindes; but why ſhould I exceede in diuiſion pretending to preach peace? but of all the reſt, why ſhould I ſo infinitely diuide that which the holy Ghoſt contracteth into one? therfore I finde this multiplicity reduced into two heads, either <hi>Habitare in vnum,</hi> ſubiectiuely into one which is God, or <hi>Habitare in vno,</hi> for things of leſſe moment, yet (if it be poſsible) to agree in one; Into God, one God, one faith we are neceſſarily grafted as into a ſtocke, without which there is no peace, no religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no loue, no life; and for other things, though not ſo neceſſarie, yet Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts to be of <hi>one minde,</hi> and <hi>one iudgement, Philip.</hi> 2. Therefore if it be poſsible, let vs <hi>Habitare in vno,</hi> all to follow one way, one gouernment, one diſcipline: but howſoeuer it fall, let vs <hi>Habitare in vnum,</hi> ſtill to hold our grounds, one Goſpell, one Faith, one God: that is, if we can, let vs all agree in an vniformitie, but if not ſo, yet let vs ſtil hold
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2911:9"/> the grounds of vnitie: yea, and though we cannot <hi>Habitare in vno;</hi> that is, to keepe all one faſhion, yet becauſe we are all of one faith, to hold euen our differences in peace, and to doe nothing through contention.</p>
            <p>The limiting of peace is onely among <hi>brethren;</hi> which becauſe it is a word of great equiuocation, the diſtinguiſhing of the kindes of brethren, will ſort out the diuers kindes of peace; therefore firſt there bee brethren by creation, and ſo we be all, as we be all the ſonnes of one God; for as it is <hi>Malach.</hi> 2: haue we not all one father! hath not one God made vs all? and thus wee are all tied to peace, ſo farre as peace is taken for a meere ceſſation from warre, for to that purpoſe ſpeaketh <hi>Saint Paul, Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>If it be poſsible and as much as in you lieth haue peace with all men;</hi> yea, there is a kinde of peace to be maintained euen with Turkes, and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and wee haue no reaſon to inuade the poſſeſsions of Infidels, only for being Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, but rather to liue brotherly and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely by them, becauſe they bee men: Why, but did not the Iſraelites inuade the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2911:9"/> land of <hi>Canaan?</hi> it is true, they did ſo; yet they had for ſo doing a ſpeciall command from God: but what reaſon had <hi>Dauid</hi> to make warre vpon the <hi>Ammonites?</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. he had for his warrant a prouocation from themſelues, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. and in ſuch caſes with ſuch brethren it is lawfull to breake the peace, but otherwiſe as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cùm tu Chriſtianus Paganu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpolias &amp;c.</hi> When thou a Chriſtian doſt rob and ſpoile a Pagan, thou robbeſt God of a conuert, &amp; as much as in thee lieth, thou diuerteſt a Pagan from being a Chriſtian. Secondly, there be bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by bloud, either deſcended all imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately of one father, as <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſons <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. <hi>We be</hi> 12. <hi>brethren, the ſonnes of one father,</hi> or elſe, mediately deſcended of the ſame An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, euen as <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> though but the kinſ-men of Chriſt, yet called <hi>Math.</hi> 13. the brethren of Chriſt. And by this bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood we are tied to that 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>brotherly kindneſſe:</hi> and it was the reaſon whereby <hi>Abraham</hi> perſwaded <hi>Lot</hi> to peace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. <hi>Let there be no ſtrife between thee &amp; me, for thou and I are brethren.</hi> For what ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2911:10"/> vs to liue peaceably in the world, if not this, that wee are all deſcended of one wombe, and if ſuch contend in the world, what can they doe more, vnleſſe with <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> they returne into the wombe, &amp; ſpurne, and kicke, and fight it out there. Thirdly, they are ſaid to be brethren who are all of one Countrey, <hi>Countrey-men.</hi> In which ſenſe God ſpeaketh, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. <hi>To a Stranger thou maiſt lend on vſury, but not vnto thy brother,</hi> that is, vnto thy fellow Iſraelite: now the vnion of ſuch brethren is the ſtrength of the kingdome, but when ſuch fall off, it is a kingdome diuided, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand. In the Sciſme betwixt <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Gilead</hi> there fell in one fielde two and forty thouſand, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 12. and the falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the ten Tribes from the two, was occaſionally the ruine of both the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; and hee that readeth our Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſhall finde that we Engliſh and Scots haue ſpent more bloud in domeſticall broiles, then when one of vs in time of hoſtilitie oppoſed an other, but now it is peace here, and peace at home, and when
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2911:10"/> we Engliſh ſhall returne home, and call to minde how kindly our Scottiſh brethren haue vſed vs here, we cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their kindneſſe, and owne them as brethren, yea if nationall brotherhood could not, yet very ſhame ſhall driue vs now to loue both them &amp; our ſelues more mutually at home. Fourthly, they are ſaid to be brethren who are al of one profeſsion, &amp; in that ſenſe, Kings who vnder God diuide the earth, do call each other brethren; yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen when the two kings had newly fought a bloudy field, the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> asked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the King of <hi>Aram, Is my brother yet aliue?</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20. And there is nothing more needfull either for Church or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, then that Kings do liue peac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, and as brethren; for when it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Delirant Reges, plectuntur Achiui:</hi> great and mightie men runne a madding, and the poore Peaſant muſt pay for it, &amp; while <hi>Benhadad</hi> ſitteth quaffing in his tent, his Captaine and his Souldiers fall by thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in the fielde; and therefore Kings by name muſt ſo be praied for, as the <hi>people may</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2911:11"/> 
               <hi>liue honeſtly and quietly vnder them,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. but he that ſoweth ſedition between kings, or hinders their iuſt peace when it is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he is a fire-brand betweene two king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the fatherleſſe and widowes ſhall curſe him, the bloud of the maſſacred (like the bloud of <hi>Abell)</hi> ſhall cry againſt him, the God of peace ſhall confound him, and the Diuell whom hee ſerueth, in this ſhall pay him his wages. Againe as Kings, ſo the Apoſtles for their like profeſsion did call each other brethren, for ſo did <hi>Peter</hi> cal <hi>Paul his beloued brother,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. and <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith that this text bred Monaſteries, and brought the Monkes and Fryers together; but ſure he meaneth the old Monkes, and the auncient Fryers, for the later breede come not ſo high as from the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> but they may rather ſeeke themſelues, where Saint <hi>Paul</hi> vnluckily found himſelfe, <hi>Inter falſos fratres,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and as the Apoſtles, ſo we their ſucceſſors for vnitie of affection and conſent of iudgement, ought all to bee as brethren; yet not as brethren in equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for the King and his ſubiects by the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2911:11"/> mouth of God are all called brethren, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. to teach the King to thinke of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, as of brethren, &amp; yet he were a proud ſubiect that ſhould ſo equalize himſelfe, as out of that text to call the King brother, ſo brotherhood in the Church concludes no parity of Church functions; yea the peace heere mentioned is not well maintained in a parity, for ſee in the Pſalme the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of peace, and how it runnes, It begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at the <hi>head,</hi> it falleth downe by the <hi>beard,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>skirts of the cloathing;</hi> It beginneth at the head firſt, which is the high Prieſt, the figure of Chriſt, it goeth downe by the beard, the mouth of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and ſo downe to the skirts, euen to the loweſt of the people, and how ſhall the people be annointed with peace, when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> beard is defiled with ſedition, or how ſhall we build vp the people in peace, when our ſelues like the vale of the Temple are rent in ſunder? yea what ruine and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall not follow the rupture and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynting of the Eccleſiaſticall body? <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> ſaith that before the great and fearefull
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2911:12"/> perſecution vnder <hi>Diocleſian</hi> there was euen in the Church-men themſelues a prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of God vnto it, for they were all one deadly ſet againſt an other, <hi>Epiſcopi in Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, &amp; Paſtores repulſa pietatis norma &amp;c.</hi> both Byſhops, Prieſts, and people were all fiered &amp; enflamed one againſt another, &amp; then came <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> as a fire-brand caſt vp out of hell to burne and conſume them all: but let peace begin at the Prelates and Preiſts of God, and then no doubt, but the loweſt of the people ſhall bee annoynted with it. Fiftly &amp; laſtly, they are called brethren who be all of one religion; and in that ſenſe euen <hi>Paul,</hi> though a Iew and borne at <hi>Tarſus</hi> in <hi>Cilicia,</hi> yet calleth the <hi>Romans</hi> brethren; <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the mercies of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. and there is no peace like this, yea there is no peace without this: for let a man not bee at peace with God, and hee is no brother to vs, there is no dwelling with him: and that befalleth two wayes, either when men faile in fundamentall poynts of faith, or when they ſtray notoriouſly in wickedneſſe of life. If any man bring not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2911:12"/> this doctrine, bid him not God ſpeed (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn)</hi> for what comfort is in that peace which is entertained with an Infidell, an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, and Heretique, or an obſtinate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, with whom a man may eat and drink, but not at the holy table; he may be merry with him, but not ſing Pſalmes with him; he may talke with him, but he cannot pray with him; and hee may walke with him but they muſt part at the Church dore, yea there is no peace with ſuch, but when wee make peace with them, wee breake peace with God, for all peace and loue is founded firſt in religion, and in God, and if we agree not firſt in religion, all other agreement is horrible in the eyes of God. Again, though a man profeſſe the ſame faith, yet if he liue a wicked life, there is no dwelling or liuing with him. <hi>If any that is called a brother be a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator, or a drunkard, or a rayler, with ſuch an one eat not.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. with ſuch an one eat not, that is, conuerſe not; and why? firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is vncomfortable, for <hi>woe is me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) that I dwell in Meſhech,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. Secondly, it is not ſutable, for <hi>righteouſnes &amp;</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2911:13"/> 
               <hi>peace haue kiſſed,</hi> but <hi>what fellowſhip hath light with darkneſſe?</hi> Thirdly, it is not ſafe for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, for <hi>Commiſti ſunt inter gentes, &amp; dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunt opera eorum,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, euen Gods owne people were mingled with the Heathen, and learned their workes, and if we ſleepe with dogges, what maruell is it, if we riſe with fleas? yea, as the coldeſt iron comes red hot out of the fire, ſo the beſt natures are corrupted by ill company. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is not ſafe for feare of confuſion, for they which dwell in <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of her plagues. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18. euen as the marriners in the ſhip with <hi>Ionas,</hi> (though cleere of the ſinne) yet had their part in the ſtorme.</p>
            <p>Now for the commendation of peace, it is firſt reported <hi>good</hi> and then <hi>pleaſant:</hi> Firſt good, <hi>quia omnia fundantur in bono,</hi> good is the ground of euery thing; and it is good firſt as <hi>Tobit</hi> commended <hi>Raphael,</hi> to be of a good ſtocke: ſo Peace hath God to her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who ſeuen times in the Goſpell is ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The God of Peace:</hi> Againe, peace is good, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ahimaaz: a good man and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2911:13"/> 
               <hi>good tidings,</hi> So <hi>Pax in terris,</hi> is the beſt newes that euer came into the world. <hi>Luc.</hi> 3. Againe, peace is farre fetcht, for it came from heauen; and it is deere bought, euen by the blood Chriſt; and if it be ſo, that is, if farre fetcht and deere bought, yee know for whom it is good then; it ſhall then befit the greateſt Ladies, rather with <hi>Pilats</hi> wife, to perſwade their husbands to peace, then with <hi>Iobs</hi> wife and <hi>Iezabel,</hi> to make them fall out with God and man: Againe, peace is good by diuine reſemblance, for as God is in perſons three, and in ſubſtance one, euen ſo doth Chriſt pray for the Church, that according to that pattern it may be one. <hi>Io.</hi> 17. againe, peace is good by naturall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, for all other creatures are borne with a kinde of armour into the world, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hornes to gore, teeth to bite, or nailes to rend and teare, but man (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) is borne <hi>naked into the world,</hi> to ſhew a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able creature borne into it: Thus God ſent peace, heauen bred it, the Angels brought it, Chriſt Ieſus purchaſed it, when hee died he bequeathed it, and hee died to make it:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2911:14"/> this muſt needes bee good: But all theſe praiſes are externall: peace is good in it ſelfe, and <hi>In ſenſu morali,</hi> It is good, becauſe it maketh good; for firſt it buildeth vs into the Church, yea it buildeth the very Church; <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſouldier might not build the Temple. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. 3. but <hi>Salomon</hi> the peaceable; and <hi>Scotland</hi> hath now felt, that they which write <hi>Beati pacifici,</hi> haue not been the worſt friends and builders of their Church; and when <hi>Salomon</hi> built the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there was neither hammer, nor axe, nor iron to bee heard in it, while it was a building. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 6. The Phariſies and Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces were not yet come with their ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to deface and peruert the Law, nor <hi>Arrius</hi> with his axe to cut off the God-head of Chriſt, nor were there either <hi>Marcioniſts, Manichees,</hi> or <hi>Neſtorians</hi> as yet, to make a a noyſe in the Church; but all was peace: &amp; as the Temple was built vp in peace, ſo is euery Chriſtian engrafted into the Church in peace, and when wee are once in, it is meerely peace, that holds vs in, for <hi>the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſpirit is kept in the bond of peace. Epheſ.</hi> 4
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2911:14"/> and what good can we doe, while wee are not in peace? we come to Church and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare well: for <hi>if yee loue on another, then are yee verily my Diſciples,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. but not elſe. Againe, we pray worſe, if we be not in peace, for we pray for forgiuenes with a ſtop; we ſay, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes,</hi> but dare goe no farther: and ſo we make a full point, where Chriſt made but a <hi>comma:</hi> but without peace we communicate at the holy table worſt of all, for we eat and drink at it <hi>euen to our owne damnation.</hi> but the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able man is free from all this, hee heareth profitably, he receiueth comfortably, &amp; he prayeth deuoutly, euen for his enemies and perſecutours, for ſo did <hi>Stephen</hi> euen when the ſtones and the bloud ranne downe by his eares. <hi>Acts</hi> 7. oh ſee and behold how good peace is. And as there is no Church, ſo no Common-wealth without peace, for by peace men multiply into families, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fill whole Countreyes, and Countreyes build vp Kingdomes, but warre kils vp all: for where in peace the ſonnes common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bury their fathers, the fathers in warre
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2911:15"/> oft bury their ſonnes; yea, war kils vp both Lawes and Iuſtice: When <hi>Antigonus</hi> entred <hi>Aſia</hi> with a ſtrong and mighty army, one ſalutes him at his entrance with an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent oration in praiſe of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> but <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> tolde him, he was a foole to ſpeake of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> to a King with a drawne ſword in his hand; yea, warre and contention kill vp e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen conſcience it ſelfe; for how many bee there, who while they bee not ſtirred, liue like Saints and Angels, but being once hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they offend God and man, and fall to plots and fowle practiſes, and become foxes and lyons in warre, who were lambs in peace; euen as <hi>Dauid,</hi> who had hee not ſmelt too much of the ſword, could neuer haue conſpired againſt <hi>Vriah</hi> as he did: but that and other things, did cleane put him by the building of the Temple; yea, warre killeth euen humanity it ſelfe, and taketh from many all ſenſe of blood and cruelty: for was it not a ſtrange ſpeech of <hi>Abner</hi> to <hi>Ioab, Let the yoong men ariſe and play:</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. and what was their play? they went out twelue to twelue, and fought ſo long that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2911:15"/> all fell down dead: but it was a cruell heart which thought killing but a play, and it was a miſerable play where all were loſers: This was nought, but peace is good.</p>
            <p>Yea, peace is not <hi>good</hi> onely, but <hi>pleaſant</hi> too: now good and pleaſant to concurre is rare, for many things are pleaſant which are not good, euen as <hi>Iob</hi> 20. <hi>wickedneſſe was ſweet in his mouth:</hi> againe, many things are good which are not pleaſant, yea, few things which are good are pleaſant: In me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines the beſt are bitter ſtill, and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid was good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. yet <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. is vnpleaſant for the time, and though it bee more bleſſed and better to giue then to take, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. yet Lawyers and all trades can tell, it is much more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to take then to giue: but good and pleaſant doe both meet heere: Now of pleaſure, the neereſt Iudge to vs is naturall ſenſe, but peace is pleaſant, and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to all the ſenſes; As firſt and for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the ſmell, for which in this Pſalme it is compared to a precious oyntment, but that which ſmelleth ſweete, euery man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2911:16"/> draweth neerer to it, euen as <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe of the ſauor of thy good ointments, we wil run after thee.</hi> So peace hath an attractiue power, for though men naturally loue their owne Countrey beſt, yet euery man liketh beſt to liue and dwell where it is peace; <hi>Izaak</hi> left <hi>Gerar</hi> when they ſtroue with him, and went to <hi>Sitnah</hi> for peace, and when they ſtroue with him there, he went to <hi>Rehoboth</hi> and <hi>Beerſheba</hi> for peace. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> can tell, and ſo I think can <hi>Scotland</hi> too, what a conflux of <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrangers hath beene to vs ſometime for the ſhadow of our peace, euen for that peace which our friends haue admired, our enemies enuied, &amp; Sathan hath often puſht at, but God hath ſo enlarged, as we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> tree, a ſhade and refuge for all the beaſts and fowles of the field. Secondly, as peace is pleaſant in ſent ſo in ſight too; <hi>Dauid</hi> when hee wrote this was not ratling in harneſſe, nor in the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid aſpect of a ſouldier, for the garriſons were all diſſolued, and the wars now done, but <hi>Dauid</hi> now was turned reueller, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2911:16"/> with a troope of gallants, thirty thouſand pickt and choſen men, he marcheth before the arke, and ſingeth, and plaieth, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, and like a Prieſt putteth on a linnen Ephod. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. oh it was a glorious ſight, and the triumph of their new atchieued peace, onely <hi>Michol</hi> ſcoffed at it, as many Schiſmitiques and ill-affected men do now, to ſee the ornaments and attires of the Church in the time of her peace; for when the Church came out of Aegypt (whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhee wore before and in the daies of her bondage) yet then being freed and ſettled, God would haue her put on <hi>ſilke and ſcarlet, and fine twined linnen. Exod.</hi> 28. and what if <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> liuing in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and lamenting the times, went vp and downe in haire-cloth, and girt with le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther girdles, muſt we now do it in the daies of our peace? no: but as <hi>Salomon</hi> was Chriſt, and <hi>Salomons</hi> houſe the Church of Chriſt in figure, ſo are wee in verity the ſeruants of that <hi>Salomon,</hi> and of that Chriſt, whoſe <hi>ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and order, and attire</hi> (though <hi>Michol</hi> ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at) yet a wiſer woman, the Queene of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2911:17"/> 
               <hi>Sheba</hi> admired; 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wee, wee I ſay (for I keepe not others vine, nor med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with other Churches) but wee of the Church of <hi>England</hi> do ſerue and miniſter to God in white, &amp; yet we neither reuiue the dead rites of the Iewes, nor temporize with the popiſh Churches, but we weare white by the Text, partly to ſignifie the pureneſſe and integrity which ſhould be, as <hi>Reu.</hi> 19. 8 and partly to giue thankes to God, and to teſtifie our reioycing for the peace of the Church, which is, according to that which is written <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 8. Thirdly, peace is pleaſant to the eares too; for define peace, and it is but harmony, and the beſt harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is of high and low, and baſe and meane, &amp;c. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayd <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. <hi>Hee would ſing of mercy and iudgment.</hi> A ſtrang kinde of skill to put mercy &amp; iudgement both i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſong, but it was in muſike, &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> was the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. and the beſt Muſician that euer was in the world; and as Muſique is nothing elſe but harmony or agreement of diſagreeing parts, ſo is peace. Peace in the body is a due temperature of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2911:17"/> contrary humours, peace in the minde is a concurrence of affection with reaſon, peace in the man is a body ſubdued to the ſoule; peace among men is when the ſuperiours gouerne iuſtly, when inferiours obey wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and equals loue mutually, &amp; peace in the Church is, when there is one God, one faith, one heart: when they whom God hath placed aboue, are obeyed as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and they beneath are reſpected as brethren; when one plants, and another waters; when one preacheth a truth, and another comes and confirmes it, this is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and this is peace: but Heretiques and Schiſmatiques ſtill ſing out of tune. Fourthly, peace is pleaſant to the feeling too, that is, it is profitable, for which in this Pſalme it is compared to the <hi>deaw of Hermon, which made the mountaines fruitfull.</hi> But warre (as one compares it) is like the Baſiliske, which ſcorcheth and poyſoneth the very graſſe, and the ground whereon he goeth, ſo warre depopulates and deſtroyes all; we neede not ſeeke farre for witneſſe; witneſſe in our Scottiſh and Engliſh borders, the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2911:18"/> woods and forreſts waſted, the fields yet vntilled, the townes yet vnbuilt, and for townes and houſes meere kennels for dogs, ſhrowdes fit for beaſts, but farre vnfit for men, and yet we ſee in our trauels no great ſuperfluity of beaſts neither, onely they were beaſts which made this deſolation, and whoſoeuer were captaines and ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Diuell on both ſides was leader of the field: Nay, let it be but a ſuit in Law, and it is wonderfull to ſee how a man wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth by it; one Lawyer muſt bee feed, <hi>Ne noceat,</hi> that hee doe no hurt, and another takes a fee, and doth in truth a very little good; and money runnes while all be run out, and the fees of the ſuit exceede many times the benefit of the ſentence, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a man becomes poore at the victory, who had beene rich, if hee had forborne the combate, but in peace men plant and build, and ſow, and reape, and grow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding rich, and as in the peaceable daies of <hi>Salomon, Euery man ſits vnder his vine and his fig-tree, and there is none to make afraid.</hi> Fiftly and laſtly, peace is pleaſant to the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2911:18"/> taſte too: I ſpeake it in the ſenſe of <hi>Dauid. Pſal.</hi> 34. <hi>O taſte and ſee how gracious the Lord is,</hi> the taſte and reliſh of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for hee that is not in peace, hath his conſcience full of horror: If he but ſee ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proſper, he is afflicted at it, but if hee ſee it continue, hee plotteth and practiſeth how to impeach it: yea, <hi>Saul</hi> was more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Dauids</hi> riſing, then at all which the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> did againſt him; yea, <hi>Haman</hi> was not aſhamed to confeſſe, that his riches, &amp; his children, and his honours, and all the grace the King had done him, yet did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing auaile him, ſo long as <hi>Mardochai</hi> was in his eye. <hi>Eſter</hi> 5. oh how ill taſted is that, which takes away the taſte of all other pleaſures from vs: but the peaceable min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man is free from all this, hee taſteth pleaſures in his prayers, he taſteth pleaſure in his ſleep, yea, he lies him down &amp; ſleeps in peace. Pſal. 4. hee enuieth no man, but ſaith with <hi>Dauid, we haue wiſhed you good luck,</hi> euen to the ten Tribes that were againſt him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. he asketh not the death of his enemy, much leſſe contriueth it, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2911:19"/> though he haue <hi>Saul</hi> in the cane, yet he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his aduantage, and letteth him goe, and hee that can doe thus, when hee dieth ſhall finde it true, which <hi>Abigail</hi> ſayd to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> It ſhall bee no greefe of minde to thee, that thou haſt not auenged thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The fourth poynt generall is, that peace is not onely commended good, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, behold <hi>How</hi> good, and <hi>How</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; for as <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nyſius</hi> ſayth of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in a viſion, hee that thinketh hee hath ſeene God <hi>non vidit Deum, ſed aliquid Dei,</hi> he did not ſee God, but ſome glimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him, ſo that peace whoſe goodnes a man may limit and determine, it is not the true peace, but ſome ſhadow of it, for that peace paſſeth all vnderſtanding; and indeede to bee good, is the meaneſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation that can be giuen to any thing, for God made nothing, but what was good, and that which is not good is of the Diuell: but the poynt is heere, <hi>How</hi> good, and <hi>How</hi> pleaſant which is ſpoken by way of admiration, &amp; may admit a four-fold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, &amp; firſt with a reference to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2911:19"/> ſtory, for when wee ſee a thing come to paſſe, which paſſeth common power, yea, and our expectation too, wee fall a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſtraight, euen ſo doth <hi>Dauid</hi> heere, that <hi>Ruben,</hi> and <hi>Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> and <hi>Aſher,</hi> and <hi>Zebulon,</hi> and <hi>Nepthali,</hi> and all the Tribes ſhould come in to <hi>Iudah,</hi> and tenne ſubmit themſelues to one or two, this was good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, but <hi>How</hi> good? <hi>A Domino factum est iſtud,</hi> this was no wit, nor policy, nor pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of man, but a worke wrought by the hand of God; and to draw this to our ſelues and our owne vſe: when God at any time hath compoſed any trouble in the ſtate, any faction or perſecution in the Church, or hath made any peace which wee expected not, how can we do leſſe, then lift vp harts, and hands, and eyes to God, and wonder at it: or ſecondly this ſtrange demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, behold <hi>How</hi> good, is but an exceſsiue kinde of praiſe: and the higheſt ſtile of praiſe is to profeſſe our vnability of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, euen as the Pſalmiſt vſeth to ſpeake of God, O <hi>how</hi> excellent is thy name, and <hi>how</hi> great is thy goodneſſe? he could not com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehend
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2911:20"/> the one, nor was hee able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the other: ſo ſince we cannot ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſet out the praiſe of peace, wee will onely aske <hi>how</hi> good it is, and praiſe it by ſaying nothing of it. Or thirdly, this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration comes in by way of obiurgation, as if hee ſayd, Oh yee that know not how good peace is, beholde and conſider how good it is; for wee commonly wonder at thoſe things which are vnwonted to vs, and ſince wee are ſuch ſtrangers to peace, it is ſpoken with a kinde of checke, that wee ſhould learne to know that with admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereof we cannot be ignorant, but to our great ſhame. Or elſe fourthly and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this admiration is myſticall, for as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was a figure of Chriſt, ſo <hi>Dauids</hi> peace was a figure of the peace in heauen, euen of that peace which eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, and which hath not entred into the heart of man, but as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of it, <hi>Facilius eſt conſequi quam ennarrare,</hi> it ſhall be eaſier to attaine it, then to define it: &amp; therfore ſince we can only aske que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of it, <hi>How</hi> good, and <hi>How</hi> pleaſant,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2911:20"/> but cannot anſwer, when we haue asked, our way is onely to beleeue it, and ſo to liue, as they that expect and looke for it.</p>
            <p>And ſo we come to the laſt point, <hi>Behold,</hi> which though in ranke &amp; order of words it ſtand firſt, yet ariſing out of the Text, as an vſe out of the doctrine, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in good method to be handled laſt: for peace being ſo good &amp; ſo pleaſant, how can we do leſſe then looke vpon it. <hi>Behold</hi> how good, &amp;c. <hi>Behold:</hi> how! why Behold in contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of minde, or behold in experience; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in vnderſtanding, or behold in ſenſe; Behold it, that is, ſearch or ſeeke to know it; or elſe behold it, that is, onely looke out and ſee it; Behold it with the minde firſt, for it is true in euery thing, <hi>Quantum intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur tantum diligitur;</hi> wee loue things ſo farre as we know them, but no man can extend his loue beyond his knowledge, <hi>The ſonnes of God ſaw the daughters of men,</hi> and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came enamoured of them, but if they had not ſeen them, they had neuer loued them; and <hi>Dauid</hi> where hee profeſſeth to loue the Law, ſheweth the reaſon of it, <hi>for it was his</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2911:21"/> 
               <hi>continuall meditation, Pſal.</hi> 119. that is, hee did nothing but ſtudy it, and it is the cauſe of all profaneneſſe in the world, that men doe not extend their conſideration to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the goodneſſe of God, and the beauty of vertue; <hi>The timbrell, pipe and wine are in their feaſts</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay) but they conſider not the works of the Lord. Eſa.</hi> 5. But if thou knoweſt the gift of God, ſaith Chriſt to the woman of <hi>Samaria. Ioh.</hi> 4. and againe, had they known the myſtery of the Goſpell, they would not haue crucified the Lord of glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. yea, and for peace, <hi>Oh if thou hadſt knowne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt) the things that belong vnto thy peace. Luc.</hi> 19. for if men did behold Peace in her perfect beauty, and conſider of what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt it hath euer beene in the Church, they would not breake the peace as they doe; that is, they would not fall out for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, nor forſake the vnity of the Church for their owne fancies, nor write, nor raile, nor preach one againſt another, nor ſpurne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt authority as they doe; for the holy Apoſtles ſtrained farre to keepe peace, and <hi>ſaluafide,</hi> became all things to all, rather then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2911:21"/> to breake the peace: and in the primitiue Church they profeſſed it leſſe hainous to ſacrifice to Idols, then to breake the peace: but now as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd to the Church at <hi>Corinth:</hi> we haue all knowledge, and know all things. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. wee know how to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the Church, and wee know how to make combuſtion, and to ſtirre vp ſedition, and to ſet both Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth on fire, but no man beholds or knowes how good &amp; how pleaſant peace is. Againe, beholding heere is not onely conſidering, but <hi>Dauids</hi> meaning is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it in ſenſe, for <hi>Iſhbofeth</hi> and he ſought both for a kingdome, but they ſought it with their ſwords, and ſo loſt peace, but now they haue recouered it, eſpecially <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> for his part, and to that point he ſpeaks, and he ſpeakes it with his finger, <hi>Ecce, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> in ſenſe, how good peace is; for indeed to behold it in ſpeculation onely, that is, to behold it, and not to haue it, what a behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding call you this? yea, to behold peace, as the beggerly Philoſophers did write their politiques &amp; ſpeculate of Kingdomes, &amp; as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2911:22"/> poore Mathematicians turne heauen and earth about in a globe, and then want mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to buy a loafe of bread, this is a colde contemplation: yea, thus to behold peace that is, to ſee the goodneſſe of it, and then to want it, oh it is one of the plagues of hell: but <hi>Behold</hi> it (ſaith <hi>Dauid)</hi> that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and ſee how God hath ſent it: euen as <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. <hi>Bleſſed are your eyes, for they ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this beholding is with thankes, which if it be not an onely cauſe, yet ought it to be one vſe of our meeting in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and all the curſes of vnthankfulnes ſhall light vpon vs, if thus beholding peace we be not thankfull for it: and what cauſe haue we of thankes, I refer it to you Lords, Knights, and Gentle-men, Beloued and Chriſtian brethren of both Kingdomes: Two things in this Iland hath bin much &amp; long affected: one eſpecially by vs Engliſh, that God would at length combine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the two diſagreeing Families of <hi>Yorke</hi> &amp; <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> by whoſe ſchiſme and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch effuſion of blood ſo many yeeres was made. The other, that God by ſome
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2911:22"/> good meanes would reduce and bring to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether theſe two great Kingdomes into one; The former though done before our dayes, yet ſtill we enioy the <hi>goodnes</hi> &amp; <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of it: but the other, theſe golden daies of ours haue ſeene the doing of it: But oh how many conſultations were there before it could bee done? It was ſeene in both Kingdomes for many reaſons good, that is, we beheld it good in ſpeculation, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny motions and meanes were made, and much endeauour was to doe it, but the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell who breakes off all good purpoſes, and we our ſelues ſtill backward enough to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, found means euermore to ſtand aloofe, and to miſchieue one another; and when truces were taken, yet were they but the binding of Sathan for a time, for time ſtill vndid what time had done; but now it is done, and wee behold peace in ſight, and ſee peace, not as our neigbours the <hi>States,</hi> nor as the Churches in <hi>France,</hi> nor as the poore Churches in <hi>Greece,</hi> who ſee peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and want it at home, and are forced either to ſtand vpon their guard, and to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2911:23"/> ſleepe with their ſwords vnder their pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, or to proſtitute themſelues to ſlauiſh conditions: but wee haue ſuch a peace as our ſelues deſired, and God hath ſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht, as onely our ſelues ſhall bee able to impeach it; and vnleſſe, as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſayd of his owne time, <hi>Niſi noſtris peccatis Barbari for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes facti,</hi> vnleſſe our ſinnes and vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe giue victory to our enemies, the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt vs,</p>
            <p>And we muſt ſo <hi>behold</hi> our peace, as wee ſee God in it; Peace indeede is like <hi>a precious oyntment,</hi> but it is alſo <hi>like the deaw vpon the mountaines:</hi> the oyntment is powred on by the hand of a man, and our peace is well promoted by inferiour meanes: but the deaw comes from heauen, and it is God that ſendeth it, and from God in heauen comes this our peace and vnion. <hi>Who would haue ſayd to Abraham, that Sarah ſhould haue borne him a ſonne? Gen.</hi> 21. and who of late when he ſaw in <hi>England,</hi> a King with a ſonne and two daughters, all like enough to liue, and leaue a royall iſſue, who would haue ſayd to <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>Scotland</hi> euen in that age
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2911:23"/> ſhould haue bred and brought them vp a King? but God, that God <hi>(by whom Kings raigne)</hi> hath thus deuolued it for our good: and if God haue coupled vs, who then ſhal put aſunder what God hath ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? yea, what man either for his owne, or for the common good would haue this vnion ſundred? while we were diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to parts, that ſome followed <hi>Tibui,</hi> and ſome followed <hi>Omri,</hi> that ſome were for <hi>Saul,</hi> and ſome for <hi>Dauid,</hi> and one part <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> we were not ſtrangers on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but enemies too? and our very names were mutually odious; our borders were like the piller which <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> pitcht vp, as a barre to keepe the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a barre indeede to keepe out peace, but what could then debarre vs from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheeuing one another; but God, the God of peace, hath now ſounded a retraite, for where before the very ground of one was ſtill a ſnare to the other, our houſes now are become mutuall harbours, our Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are reciprocally conferring their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, yea, and our pulpits open each for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2911:24"/> other; ours of late for you, and yours now for vs, for our Prelates, and for our Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and for me alſo now, the meaneſt of ten thouſand, to commend and plead for peace; and let the hugeſt of theſe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines drop downe vpon his head, which openeth his mouth to ſpeake againſt it.</p>
            <p>Oh you that haue trauelled far, &amp; ſeen in your trauels the confines and diuiſions of other Countreyes: Tell mee, did yee euer ſee in any two Kingdomes ſo little cauſe of diuiſion, yea of diſtinction, as in ours? There are no huge <hi>Pyrenean</hi> hils or moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to diuide vs, as betwixt the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> vnleſſe pride of heart ſtand vp as a hill betwixt vs: nor are we ſeuered with wilde forreſts or <hi>Herculean</hi> woods, as <hi>Bohemia</hi> is from <hi>Germany,</hi> vnleſſe our ſelues grow wood-mad with enuy, and enuy creepe vp and downe, as a wild beaſt betwixt vs; nor are wee walled aſunder as <hi>China</hi> is from <hi>Aſia,</hi> vnleſſe ſome <hi>Hiel</hi> or <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelite</hi> ſhall ariſe, and build againe the walls of <hi>Iericho,</hi> nor is the confuſion of <hi>Babel</hi> falne vpon vs, to make vs different language,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2911:24"/> onely one ſaith <hi>Sibboleth,</hi> and the other <hi>Shiboleth,</hi> very meane and inſenſible diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences: and I hope we ſhall not be ſo mad (as <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Gilead)</hi> to fight a field for theſe; yea, if the Diuell doe not put more oddes in our hearts, then God hath done in our mouths, we ſhall need no French com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or interpreter to ſtand betweene vs, wee ſhall with little helpe vnderſtand each other, we ſhall ſpeake, and talke, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe familiarly, and loue and liue together: Laſtly, there is no raging <hi>Ocean</hi> or ſea to ſunder vs, as betwixt vs and the <hi>Indies,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we rage in hatred one againſt another; onely there runnes a pleaſant <hi>Siloam,</hi> or <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron</hi> betwixt vs; you call it <hi>Tweade,</hi> I thinke it came from twayed, becauſe by it we are made vnkindly two, but when the bridge is finiſht, Twayed ſhall then be Tyed, and we ſhall all be one; wee are not the ſonnes of <hi>Hamilcar,</hi> who ſwore <hi>Hannibal</hi> yet a childe, that hee ſhould neuer bee at peace with the <hi>Romans,</hi> which oath hee tooke at the altar, and kept to the end, but wee are not ſo; Popiſh ignorance of olde time
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2911:25"/> made vs enemies, and the Pope who makes warre and peace (as beſt may ſerue his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) he (I thinke) did little good to make vs friends; but we haue now ſhaken of him, as the Prince of contention and darkneſſe, and being better inſtructed, we haue done better, and better knowledge hath brought forth better fruits; and it will euer be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the ages to come, that one and the ſame age hath both freed vs from the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the Pope, &amp; knit vs both into one Kingdome: <hi>A Domino factum eſt iſtud:</hi> this peace is like the deaw, and diſtilled euen from the hand of God: Bleſſed be that God that ſent it, bleſſed bee the man that makes it, &amp; bleſſed be they all which do embrace it: &amp; God Almighty makes vs all ſo to dwel &amp; liue together here, that we may liue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the Kingdom of Chriſt Ieſus heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; to whom for our meeting at this time, for our ioyfull meeting in this Kingdom, &amp; for all the bleſſings ſeuerally, and for the peace now iointly beſtowed vpon vs, to him (I ſay) with the father &amp; the holy Ghoſt, be all thanks &amp; praiſe, now &amp; for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2911:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
